This is Morocco, a country that
generally looks pretty normal on most
world maps until you zoom in way closer
on the country's north coast. Where
you'll notice these two weird little
enclaves that aren't actually a part of
Morocco, but are pockets of Spain in the
European Union instead. These two
pockets are known as Ceuta and Melilla
respectively. They are the only two
pockets of European controlled territory
that still remain on the African
continent today, making up the European
Union's only physical land borders in
Africa. And they are way, way, way more
controversial and contentious than you
probably know. Combined, the two
territories are geographically small at
only about 31 square kilometers, about
the same size as the special
administrative region of Macau in China.
But like Macau, they are very densely
populated. With Ceuta having an
estimated population of about 85,000
people and Melilla having one of about
86,000 people today, they together have
more than 171,000
people between them. Who are all
citizens of both Spain and the EU,
despite living on a continent that is
distinctly not Europe and only sharing a
border with Morocco.
Life in both cities, for the most part,
feels very Spanish and European. The
architecture, culture, food, and spoken
language all seem pretty much the same
as most anywhere else in southern Spain
does. Until you get out to their edges
and you encounter their gigantic border
walls that physically isolate them from
Morocco and the rest of Africa.
Stretching across their entire land
borders with Morocco, the walls consist
of parallel double fences that soar 6
meters or 20 feet high that historically
have been topped with barbed wire.
Complete with regular guard towers and
patrols of thousands of Spanish border
guards. Beneath the ground, a vast
network of cables connect floodlights,
motion and noise sensors and 24-hour
video cameras to a central command
station. While dozens of Spanish Coast
Guard vessels constantly patrol the
coasts. A large, coordinated, and
complicated system that is explicitly
designed to keep people out of them from
the other side in Africa. The walls
effectively make both Ceuta and Melilla
isolated islands of the EU and Spain in
Africa. And if you look more closely at
their borders in Google Maps, you'll
notice that they both appear as dashed,
[music]
which symbolizes them as being disputed
because Morocco claims both of them in
their entirety and has disputed their
ownership with Spain for decades now.
On the surface of it, you might be more
inclined to side with Morocco's stands
on the dispute. Morocco asserts that
these two cities are the final living
remnants of European colonialism in
Africa today and that they therefore
should be surrendered to them. While
Spain asserts that they are both core
integral territories of Spain just as
much as anywhere else in the Spanish and
European mainland are. And caught in
between the crossfire of this
geopolitical dispute over the past
several years have been thousands of
migrants from all around the world who
have been treated by both sides as
effectively sacrificial, disposable
pawns in their own great game, which has
led to hundreds of deaths at these
heavily fortified borders over just the
past few years. That have made them not
only the deadliest borders anywhere in
the EU, but among the most blood-soaked
borders anywhere on the Earth during the
entire 21st century. [music] And yet,
somehow, these disputed and deadly
borders at the frontiers of Europe and
Africa have attracted very little
international attention. And if you'd
like to understand what's going on here
today like I did when I first heard
about them, you need to understand the
history that got us here to this strange
point today.
Ceuta, in particular, is one of the two
key strategic locations to control,
along with Gibraltar, in order to
dominate access through the nearby
narrow Strait of Gibraltar, the only
natural passageway between the
Mediterranean and the Atlantic. Ceuta is
a winding narrow peninsula that juts out
from the African mainland, which also
makes it a highly defensible position
from the rest of Africa. In the 8th
century AD, Ceuta was used as the
launchpad for the Muslim conquest of the
Iberian Peninsula that would last for
the next 800 years. During the
Reconquista, when the Christian kingdoms
of Iberia were pushing the Muslims out,
the Portuguese advanced across the
Strait of Gibraltar to seize and conquer
Ceuta in 1415,
marking the very start of modern
European expansion into Africa that
would reach its apex [music] centuries
later when nearly the entire continent
would be conquered. Decades later, the
final Muslim stronghold in Iberia,
Granada, was conquered by the Spanish in
1492. And then a few years later, in
1497, seeking to establish a forward
defensive outpost to keep the Strait of
Gibraltar secure and to prevent Muslim
powers in North Africa from regrouping,
the Spanish sailed across the
Mediterranean and conquered their own
exclave around Melilla. Then about a
century later, between 1580 and 1640,
Portugal and Spain entered into the
Iberian Union together, during which
Ceuta ostensibly remained a part of
Portugal but was subordinated under
Spanish leadership. Across this time
period, Ceuta attracted a lot of new
residents of Spanish origin. So, by the
time when the Iberian Union collapsed in
1640, Ceuta had become more
demographically Spanish than it had been
Portuguese. And so, it became the only
Portuguese territory that sided with
Spain in the aftermath. In 1668,
Portugal finally formally recognized the
allegiance of Ceuta to Spain and agreed
to cede the city to the Spanish through
the 1668 Treaty of Lisbon.
For centuries, both Ceuta and Melilla
were generally treated by the Spanish as
frontier military forts and or penal
colonies, posts to to the Spanish
mainland from Barbary piracy and
possible attacks coming from North
Africa, and also dumping grounds for
Spain's most undesirable prisoners and
outcasts to remove them away from the
mainland. For centuries, the Arabs and
the Berbers in North Africa also
attempted to reconquer both Ceuta and
Melilla through multiple sieges,
including the longest continuous siege
of a city in all of history when Ceuta
was placed under siege for 33 straight
[music] years between 1694 and 1727.
Though none were ever actually
successful in driving the Spanish out.
Much later in 1859, further
disagreements over the borders between
Ceuta and Melilla and the Kingdom of
Morocco led to a devastating war that
resulted in thousands of deaths and
ended in a decisive Spanish military
victory, which was enough to force
Morocco into signing the Treaty of Wad
Ras in 1860 that for the first time
extended Morocco's formal recognition of
Spain's sovereignty over both Ceuta and
Melilla
>> [music]
>> and set their current borders as we know
them today. As the European scramble for
Africa continued across the late 19th
and early 20th centuries, Morocco
eventually yielded to the unbearable
colonial pressures that were being
placed upon it in 1912 when it agreed
under duress to become divided between a
new French protectorate and a new
smaller Spanish protectorate. These two
protectorates placed over Morocco and
Spain's previously acquired territories
in Ceuta and Melilla were never
commingled together. They never became a
part of Spain's colonial protectorate in
Morocco and were always considered by
the Spanish to be separate integral
territories of Spain itself.
>> [music]
>> Decades later in 1956 when the
protectorate was dissolved and Morocco
regained their independence from both
France and Spain [music] again, Spain
continued holding onto its control over
both Ceuta and Melilla based on their
argument that they had never been a part
of the Moroccan protectorate and that
they had been directly controlled by
Spain for centuries. [music]
Well before the 19th century era of
European colonialism in Africa had even
begun. Spain argued, and continues to
argue, that Ceuta and Melilla are not
the results of European colonialism in
Africa, but [music] are instead
historically integral territories of
Spain that have been a part of the
country for about the same length of
time as cities like Granada have been on
the Spanish mainland for more than a
half millennium now. Morocco, on the
other hand, immediately disagreed with
this position after their 1956
independence. And despite previous
treaties they had agreed to with Spain
that recognized Spanish sovereignty over
them, like the 1860 Treaty of Wad Ras,
the modern post-independence state of
Morocco insisted and continues to insist
that both Ceuta and Melilla are actually
products of European colonialism in
Africa. And based on that, Morocco has
insisted that Spain's continued control
over them is illegitimate today. Morocco
has instead maintained their own
territorial claims to both of them, and
has for decades now demanded that Spain
fully cede and transfer them both over,
which Spain has kept on refusing to do.
The gist of the modern territorial
dispute between them that continues to
this day.
I think it's also rather interesting to
point out here that Spain basically
maintains opposite hypocritical legal
arguments for why they should be able to
maintain Ceuta and Melilla, but also why
the UK should return Gibraltar back to
them. On the opposite side of the strait
from Ceuta, the British conquered from
Spain centuries ago back in 1704, and
have controlled it ever since. Spain
currently argues that the continued
presence of the British in Gibraltar is
an illegitimate legacy of British
imperialism that interrupts with their
own territorial contiguity, and
therefore that the UK should return the
territory back to Spain again. Well,
Britain insists that the territory is an
integral part of the UK that has been
British for centuries now, and then
almost everybody who lives there are
British citizens who have no desire to
join with Spain, which is all basically
an exact mirror of Spain and Morocco's
disputes on the other side of the strait
over Ceuta and Melilla in North Africa.
In both instances, Spain takes precisely
opposite legal arguments whenever it
conveniently benefits them more, which I
thought was a silly but worthy tangent
to throw in here.
As it's proven over the decades,
however, Spain's continued over Ceuta
and Melilla have never ended up becoming
as controversial as other contentious
borders drawn up by Europeans in the
Arab world did, like French Algeria or
Israel. Their control over these cities
doesn't really harm Spanish relations
with anybody else in the greater Arab
world beyond Morocco. While Spain could
never conceivably agree to just give up
these territories to Morocco, where
roughly 170,000
of their own citizens currently live.
The people of both cities, shown in poll
after poll over the years,
overwhelmingly would rather remain a
part of Spain and the EU and all of the
benefits that entails, rather than
becoming a part of Morocco. Under most
international conventions, transferring
over the cities to Moroccan control
would require hosting a referendum in
them, which as you can imagine would
never possibly be successful right now.
And Morocco also knows full and well
that an outright invasion of the
territories would spark a massive
international crisis that would almost
certainly lose as well. While neither
Ceuta nor Melilla are considered to be
legally under NATO's protection since
they're physically located beyond
Europe, Spain itself is very capable of
defending them all on their own. Ceuta
in particular is only located 17 km away
from the Spanish mainland and is located
relatively nearby to the primary Spanish
naval base at Rota, as well as the
Spanish Air Force's key air base at
Morón. Spain can very easily and very
effectively project naval and air power
into both Ceuta and Melilla to defend
them if need be. And with a military
budget well more than double the size of
Morocco's and the likely backing of the
rest of the EU, Morocco knows that they
would be hopelessly outclassed if they
ever attempted to take the cities
through force, which is why they never
try to do that and why they resorted to
covert hybrid warfare operations against
them instead.
Initially, upon Morocco's independence,
Spain granted Moroccans the right to
travel back and forth between Melilla
and Ceuta for work and travel relatively
freely. And the issue of Morocco's claim
to both of the territories more or less
faded away into the background of
international affairs until the 1990s,
>> [music]
>> when Spain joined the EU and then the
Schengen area, which enabled
passport-free travel between them. After
neighboring Algeria collapsed into a
devastating civil war throughout the
1990s around the same time, a new surge
of migration began of refugees fleeing
that war across the border towards
Melilla, which at only 70 km away from
the Algerian border was easily the
closest EU territory to the country and
the easiest pathway for refugees to take
into the rest of Europe through the
Schengen area. Spain then quickly began
receiving pressure from Brussels to cut
down on the flows of migrants that were
entering into the EU through Melilla.
And so, beginning in 1996, Spain started
the construction of what was initially a
3-m high chain-link double fence across
just 7 mi of the Melilla border.
>> [music]
>> By 1998, the first phase of the modern
wall around the exclaves was finished.
But because of Melilla's rough, hilly
topography, the fence wasn't constructed
along the exactly agreed-upon border
with Morocco. Instead, it was
constructed along an approximation of
the border, meaning that in a few
instances, some of the Spanish residents
of Melilla in the '90s suddenly found
their homes on the wrong side of the
fence, facing towards Morocco exposed.
Since then, as the pace of migration
into Ceuta and Melilla from sub-Saharan
Africa and the Middle East has increased
as the pathways into the EU they
represent have become more desirable,
especially as a way to avoid the much
more dangerous way of crossing over the
Mediterranean Sea, [music] the Spanish
authorities have been increasingly added
to the wall's sophistication, making
Ceuta and Melilla increasingly more
difficult fortresses to reach for anyone
from beyond the EU. By 2005, the fences'
height around both Melilla and Ceuta was
doubled up to 6 m, and it was finally
expanded to fully envelop the entire
length of their borders. By 2014,
anti-climb mesh was installed, and parts
of the wall were topped off with barbed
wire. Well, by 2020, parts of the walls'
heights were further increased up to 9
m. And throughout it all, as the walls'
complexities evolved, the violence and
tragedies experienced along them
continued escalating as well.
>> [music]
>> Tensions between Spain and Morocco over
these disputed territories really began
escalating in 2002, when a group of
armed Moroccan soldiers occupied the
small, uninhabited island nearby to
Ceuta that is similarly [clears throat]
under Spanish sovereignty but disputed
by Morocco. The Moroccan soldiers
hoisted a Moroccan flag on the island,
which was noticed by a passing Spanish
Coast Guard vessel on its routine
patrol. The Spaniards landed on the
island and were confronted by the
Moroccans, who forced them back onto
their boat at gunpoint after what was
reportedly a heated argument. Over the
next few days, the Moroccan soldiers on
the island built up a fixed base on it,
while the Spanish government warned that
it would not accept a Moroccan fait
accompli taking control over the island.
Spain sent in naval reinforcements to
Ceuta, and a week after the Moroccans
occupied the island, Spain launched a
large military operation code named
Romeo Sierra to evict them and retake
it. Four Eurocopter Cougar helicopters
departed from the Spanish mainland early
in the morning and landed dozens of
Spanish special forces on the occupied
island. While Spanish F-18 and Mirage F1
fighters flew overhead to provide aerial
cover just in case the Moroccan Air
Force attempted to interfere. The
special forces were under direct orders
to do their best to achieve the
recapture of the island with zero
casualties, but they were still well
armed and permitted to use lethal force
if they were fired upon by the Moroccans
first. In the end though, the Moroccan
soldiers on the island offered up almost
no resistance and rapidly surrendered.
They were all taken prisoner and
returned back to Morocco and the Spanish
retook control over the island without a
shot having to be fired. The whole
incident showed that military clashes
between the Moroccans and the Spanish
over these disputed territories were
still possible even in the 21st century.
Since then, the Moroccans haven't
attempted to occupy the island again,
but the Moroccan government has also
continued to maintain its claim to it as
well. And meanwhile, as the pace of
migration into both Ceuta and Melilla
from across sub-Saharan Africa and the
Middle East through Morocco continued
growing in scale, and while Spain and
Morocco's ownership dispute over them
also continued, the borders around them
began growing increasingly deadly as
Morocco began calculating on a hybrid
warfare strategy of allowing migrants to
pass through their territory in order to
apply pressure on the territories they
wanted, while Spain continued facing
pressure from Brussels to restrict the
entry of migrants at the frontiers as
much as physically possible.
Across just three months in 2005 between
August and October, Amnesty
International reported that 13 migrants
died at the borders of Ceuta and Melilla
at the hands of Moroccan and Spanish
border police. Waiting to build up their
numbers into a critical mass. Groups of
desperate migrants would organize in
Morocco just outside of the border wall
and then rush it together in numbers as
large as dozens to hundreds at a time in
their bid to get into the EU and a
chance to apply for asylum or refugee
status. Across the deadly incidents in
2005, these migrants would often find
themselves caught in between the live
ammunition being fired by the Moroccan
border security and the rubber bullets
and tear gas being fired by the Spanish
border security. While Spain has
consistently claimed that none of their
own border guards at either Ceuta or
Melilla carry live firearms, Amnesty
International reported the testimony of
one of these migrants during the deadly
2005 incidents that it deemed was
credible in which he claimed to have
been shot and severely injured by a live
bullet that was fired by a Spanish
border guard. During another notable
incident in 2006, three migrants were
killed while attempting to cross over
the border wall into Melilla on just a
single day. One reportedly from gunshot
wounds in two more when they fell from
the top of the wall.
Then in 2007, the status of Ceuta and
Melilla triggered another diplomatic
crisis between Spain and Morocco when
the Spanish King, Juan Carlos I,
decided to physically visit both of
them. Morocco reacted to the visit very
negatively, recalling their ambassador
to Spain in protest while the Moroccan
Prime Minister attempted to even compare
Spain's control of Ceuta and Melilla
with the Israeli occupations on the West
Bank and the Gaza Strip. Though this
particular crisis petered out after only
about a month, it remained a clear
example that the contested history and
claims over Ceuta and Melilla between
Morocco and Spain still remained ever
present even in the modern era. And then
a few years later in 2014 came what
would become, up until that point, the
deadliest tragedy at the border walls
for the migrants from elsewhere getting
caught up between their history.
In February of that year, a large group
of approximately 200 migrants, refugees,
and asylum seekers from sub-Saharan
Africa attempted to swim around the
border wall of Ceuta in the cover of
darkness and night. Spanish border
guards then discovered them as they
began approaching the coast on the other
side of the wall, and then began opening
fire on the swimmers with rubber bullets
and tear gas in an attempt to drive them
away. The Spanish government would
initially try and deny that this had
happened, but surveillance footage
released later undeniably showed it
taking place. The rubber bullets and
tear gas fired into the mass of swimmers
significantly impaired their ability to
swim, which contributed to 15 of them
tragically drowning that night. The
largest loss of life during a single
crossing attempt up until that point.
And while the Spanish government
subsequently announced an investigation
into the incident, it was conducted by
the Ceuta border guards themselves, and
the case was ultimately dropped without
charging any of their own officers as
being responsible for the deaths. An
outcome that has been hotly criticized
by NGOs like Human Rights Watch and
Amnesty International ever since. In the
aftermath of this incident, the Spanish
government banned their guards in both
Ceuta and Melilla from using rubber
bullets anymore. While Morocco agreed to
cooperate further with the Spanish
authorities on restricting the flow of
migrants up to their borders in the
first place in exchange for 346 million
euros paid to them by the EU over the
next 6 years until 2020.
For several years after, the scale of
tragedy taking place at the borders
decreased. While Morocco and Spain's
cooperation on migration caused the
geopolitical dispute over Ceuta and
Melilla's ownership to fade back into
the background. But then as the COVID-19
pandemic struck the world in 2020, the
simmering conflict exploded back into
the open again. For the first time since
Morocco became an independent country in
1956, the Spanish ceased allowing
Moroccan citizens easy access across the
borders of Ceuta and Melilla in the wake
of the pandemic, a privilege that is to
date, six years later, still never been
restored. Frustrating Morocco's stance
on the issue further, the EU also agreed
to pay Morocco more than 500 million
additional euros in 2020 to continue
their cooperation on migration flows
leading into Ceuta and Melilla for the
next seven years through the end of
2027. But then, in 2021, began the
biggest crisis between Spain and Morocco
over their ownership status since the
19th century.
The crisis began in April of 2021 when
Spain welcomed Raheem Ghali, the
president of the Sahrawi Arab Democratic
Republic, into the country for medical
treatment, which was massively
controversial in Morocco. The Sahrawi
Arab Democratic Republic is claimed to
be the rightful government of the
Western Sahara territory since Spain
renounced its separate colonial
administration in the territory there in
the mid-1970s.
Almost immediately after Spain withdrew
from Western Sahara, Morocco invaded the
territory and claimed it all for
themselves. The indigenous Sahrawi
people who lived in Western Sahara
rejected this, declared the Sahrawi Arab
Democratic Republic to attempt and
govern Western Sahara instead, and have
gone on to fight a decades-long bloody
insurgency against the Moroccans that
continues to this day and has resulted
in tens of thousands of deaths. By the
1990s, the Moroccans had established de
facto control over about 70% of Western
Sahara's territory, including all of the
most populous cities, and had pushed the
Sahrawi forces out into the remaining
30% of the territory that is mostly
empty deserts and into neighboring
Mauritania and Algeria. Morocco then
constructed a vast network of ditches,
walls, and minefields across the de
facto frontier to keep the Sahrawi
forces and people out of the Western
Sahara. While sporadic attacks by the
Sahrawis along the wall has continued
for decades.
Since then, Morocco has continually
maintained their claim to all of Western
Sahara and has put forward a plan to
govern the territory as an autonomous
region of the country, while the Sahrawi
Arab Democratic Republic has continually
rejected this and still asserts that it
alone is the rightful government of the
Sahrawi people and their homeland in
Western Sahara. So, when Spain admitted
the Sahrawis leader into the country for
medical treatment in April of 2021,
Morocco interpreted it as a Spanish
endorsement of the Sahrawi cause and an
attack on what they viewed as their
territorial integrity in Western Sahara.
So, Morocco decided to respond to this
by weaponizing the migration issue in
Ceuta and Melilla again in order to
apply pressure on Spain to make them
change their course. Moroccan border
guards were ordered to stand down at the
borders and welcome anybody who wanted
to to cross towards the Spanish
territories freely. Then over the course
of just a single day, nearly 8,000
migrants managed to cross the border
from Morocco into Ceuta. Nearly 10% of
the entire population of Ceuta itself.
As the Moroccan border guards were
supposed to be cooperating with the
Spanish simply stood aside and
encouraged them to do so. The sudden
arrival of this many people in Ceuta all
at once immediately triggered an
enormous humanitarian crisis for the
Spanish who simply couldn't manage it
with their limited resources. The
Spanish authorities responded by
immediately deporting most of the
thousands who had crossed over back into
Morocco again in pretty clear violation
of Spanish and EU law that the Spanish
Supreme Court would later rule was
illegal, especially relating to the
estimated nearly 1,500 children who took
part and were deported back into Morocco
as well.
Morocco's tactic of pressuring Spain
with migration in these territories
would also ultimately prove to be very
effective. Less than a year later in
March of 2022, Spain, in an attempt to
ease their spiraling tensions with
Morocco and to re-secure their
cooperation on the migration issue
again, agreed for the very first time to
recognize Morocco's plan for Western
Sahara as an autonomous province under
Moroccan sovereignty, in effect
extending Spain's recognition of
Morocco's territorial claim to Western
Sahara for the first time as well, which
reversed Spain's previous decades-long
stance that it supported a UN-sponsored
referendum on self-determination for the
Sahrawi people instead. Morocco, of
course, ecstatically welcomed Spain's
change in policy towards the Western
Sahara issue and immediately promised
that they would return right back to
strictly enforcing the flow of migration
into Ceuta and Melilla again in
gratitude. [music]
All of which set the stage for what
would soon become by far the deadliest
single incident at the border walls of
these two exclaves in their entire
history.
Just a few months later, in June of
2022,
>> [music]
>> nearly 1,700 people, most of whom were
refugees and asylum seekers from Sudan
and South Sudan, gathered together just
outside of the border wall surrounding
Melilla. The local Moroccan authorities
had banned their locals from selling
them any food or providing them with any
taxi services and were increasingly
cracking down on them with arrests.
Fearing that they couldn't stay in
Morocco any longer and also believing
that the Moroccan authorities were still
going to be as lenient on the border
into Melilla as they had been just a few
months previously, the group decided
that their best chance at achieving
asylum was to collectively storm the
Melilla border wall together and
overwhelm it for sheer numbers.
>> [music]
>> So, at about 8:00 a.m. on the 24th of
June of 2022, they began climbing a
section of the wall that they knew had
been abandoned during the pandemic.
Hundreds of people managed to
successfully get over the first wall and
into a holding yard in between there and
the second wall on the Moroccan side of
the checkpoint. On the other side of the
holding yard was a locked metal gate
that led directly into Spain, which they
attempted to break through using a power
saw that was brought along. As more and
more of them entered into the central
holding yard, the Moroccan police formed
a perimeter around it on their side and
began aggressively firing rubber bullets
and tear gas at them. According to later
independent investigations by Lighthouse
Reports, at least 20 tear gas canisters
were fired into the crowded central
courtyard where hundreds of the migrants
had gathered. After the gate into Spain
was finally forced open, a stampede to
escape from the tear gas and the rubber
bullets began through it that caused a
brutal crowd crush as dozens of people
were pushed to the ground and trampled.
While footage released later showed
survivors being ruthlessly beaten by the
Moroccan police with batons as they laid
on the ground without even resisting.
The official Spanish report into the
incident would later conclude that a
minimum of 37 of the migrants died due
to the crowd crush at the border. While
Amnesty International's separate report
concluded that a further 77 of the
migrants still remain missing and
unaccounted for. Nearly four years after
the incident now, as of this video's
production, all 77 of them continue to
remain missing, implying that they
likely died as a result of the crowd
crush as well and were quietly buried in
mass graves somewhere on the Moroccan
side of the border unknown. Because of
this, it's likely that the true number
of people who died that day attempting
across the border into Melilla was more
like 114.
By far the highest number ever recorded
during a single incident and more than
previous entire decades worth of deaths
at the border all combined. All of which
gave the incident its now infamous
nickname, the Melilla Massacre. Out of
the 1,700 people who rushed the border
wall that day, in addition to the likely
114 of them who were killed, 603 others
managed to make it over to the other
side in Spain. 470 of whom were
immediately deported back into Morocco
and shipped off on Moroccan buses all
across the country and only 133 of whom
were able to stay and safely claim
asylum in Europe.
The Spanish government has officially
claimed that none of the 114 people who
died in the crush did so on Spanish
territory, which is a blatant non-truth.
The Spanish land registry record shows
that more than 13,000 square meters of
land in the holding yard, including the
section of the wall where the door was
opened up that triggered the crush,
belong to the Spanish state.
Nonetheless, by asserting that none of
the deaths took place on Spanish
territory, Spain and the EU have both
effectively taken the stance that the
tragedy that took place that day wasn't
actually their problem. Part of why the
violence dealt out to the migrants that
day from the Moroccan side was so severe
was because of the Moroccan government's
willingness to show that they would take
hard action to control migration in
order to maintain Spain's recognition
for their autonomy plan in Western
Sahara that they had just gained from
them a few months previously. With
Morocco still officially claiming the
territories as their own, Spain's
unwillingness to ever surrender them,
and Morocco's double game of restricting
migrants into them so long as they're
being paid and Spain maintains the
recognition of Western Sahara while also
opening up the flow of migration
whenever Spain stops paying them or does
something to piss them off, the
thousands of migrants who keep getting
caught in the middle of their game, who
are treated as nothing but disposable
pawns, will continue being the biggest
victims of what at first might have just
seemed like a curious geography quirk,
but in reality is a very serious and
deadly situation down on the ground.
Now, I also want to stress that Morocco
and Spain are, of course, known for a
lot of other things besides this current
conflict and their food culture has
absolutely got to be one of the top
things. From smoky Spanish rice with
shrimp to tapas with beef albondigas and
chimichurri butter ribeye, you can get
everything you need to cook delicious
home-cooked meals from Spain or anywhere
else just like these delivered right to
your doorstep through this video's
sponsor, HelloFresh. The concept of
HelloFresh is pretty straightforward.
You just visit the wrapper website and
select which meals you want to eat, and
then the next week an insulated box will
show up on your doorstep filled with all
the fresh, pre-portioned, and partially
prepared ingredients you need so that
you can home cook your meals way faster
than if you had wasted a bunch of time
planning your meals out, going to the
grocery store and picking out
ingredients, and then coming home and
prepping. You can also choose from a
variety of menu options to suit all your
needs and tastes. From fit and wholesome
to quick and easy, vegetarian to
family-friendly, there's something for
everyone to enjoy. And HelloFresh knows
that your plans might change and life
can get unexpectedly busy. That's why
they let you easily customize your
delivery from week to week as well,
allowing you to tailor everything to
your own schedule by adjusting your
delivery date or skipping a week
whenever you're not able to cook at
home. And best of all, the meals
themselves just taste really, really
good, too. That's the biggest reason of
all that I've been a loyal customer
myself to HelloFresh for years now, and
why I've been making meals like this
amazing buffalo spice chicken for more
than 4 years now. They're just the best
solution that I've ever found for having
regular home-cooked dinners. And if you
want to see if I'm right and improve the
way that you eat, too, now's a great
time to do so because when you click the
button here on your screen right now or
follow the link that's down below in the
description and use my code
RealLifeLoreFM
at hellofresh.com, you'll get 10 free
meals plus free shipping. Free meals
applied as discount on first box. New or
returning subscribers only. Varies by
plan. So, make sure to sign up today,
and once again, click the link below or
use my code reallifelorefm at
hellofresh.com to do so. It's a great
way to help support my channel and get
some delicious food at the same time.
And as always, thank you so much for
watching.